Volker, Julius; Papers apap285
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Julius Volker Papers
1958-1966, Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap285
3.25 cubic ft.
The Julius Volker Papers document Assemblyman Volker's work related to New York State Assembly sessions and legislation from 1958-1966, including undated material. Also included are papers relating to Mr. Volker's professional development as a lawyer.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Julius Volker, lawyer and member of the New York State Assembly, were donate to Syracuse University in 1966 in a series of deliveries. In 2006, the papers were transferred to the State University of New York at Albany M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Julius Volker was born in 1903 in Lancaster, New York. He received a bachelor of arts degree from Canisius College in 1924 and a bachelor of laws degree from Buffalo Law School in 1927. Volker was commissioned to the New York State Bar later that year. In 1931 he married Loretta O'Neill and together they raised two sons.
From 1934-1935 Volker served as a councilman for the town of Lancaster and was is justice of the peace from 1936-1939. Volker then served as town attorney from 1940-1941 and again in 1946. With other local leders and supporters, Volker helped to create the Lancaster Town Police Ambulance Service in 1953, the first volunteer ambulance service in Western New York and the first in the state to be operated by and within a police department.
In 1945, voters elected Volker to the New York State Assembly as the Republican representative from Erie County 7th district and he remained in that position until 1965. In 1966 Volker served an additional year in the New York Assembly as the Republician representative from Erie County 162nd district. During his tenure in the New York State Assembly Volker was chairman of the Committee on Codes and chairman of the Committee on Aviation and Insurance.
Following his retirement from the Assembly, Julius Volker maintained a law practice in Buffalo. He passed away approximately ten years later. One of Volker's sons, Dale Volker, was elected to the New York State Assembly in 1972 and became a New York State Senator three years later. He announced his intended retirement from the Senate in May 2010.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Julius Volker, politician and lawyer, span the years 1958-1966 and contain legislative files, special committee files, correspondence, and subject specific files relating to work in the New York State Assembly. The papers also contain printed bills, vouchers, newsletters, printed materials, and newspaper clippings related to New York State Assembly sessions. Julius Volker served in the New York State Assembly as a representative Erie County 7th district from 1945-1965 and 162nd district in 1966.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Legislation, 1958,1964-1966
Series 2 - Special Committees, 1959-1966
Series 3 - Correspondence, 1958, 1960-1961,1963-1966
Series 4 - Subject Files, 1961-1965, Undated
Series 1 is arranged chronologically, and then by legislation introduction number. Series 3 is arranged chronologically. Series 2 and Series 4 are arranged alphabeticlly.
Politics and Politicians; New York (State). Law Revision Commission; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly. Standing Committee on Codes; New York (State). Penal Law; Erie County (N.Y.); Legislative Records; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Volker, Julius; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly
- Legislation, 1958; 1964-1966; 1; 0.75 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically and then by legislation introduction number
  Scope and Contents
  Legislation introduced by Assemblyman Volker with related correspondence, notes, reports, clippings and printed matter. The dates on the finding aid correspond to the date of the respective bill's introduction, although related materials in each folder may encompass different dates.
  - To amend the social welfare law, in relation to residence requirements for public assistance and care, 1958 March 13 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 1)
  - To amend the public authorities law, in relation to enacting a labor relations law for employees of public authorities, 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 2)
  - To increase state aid to cities having a population of one hundred thousand or more inhabitants..., 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 3)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to a person operating a motor vehicle or motorcycle while in an intoxicated condition..., 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 4)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to adults shoulder harness type safety belt, 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 5)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to providing for notice to correct defective or improper lighting equipment, 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 6)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to attachment points for the rear seat of the motor vehicle, 1964 January 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 7)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to execution of search warrants, 1964 January 09 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 8)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to temporary questioning and search for weapons, 1964 January 09 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 9)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to dismissal of complaint for neglect to prosecute, 1964 January 16 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 10)
  - To amend the penal law, in relation to prohibiting lenders of money from making a charge for substitution or other changes in insurance policies, 1964 January 21 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 11)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to requiring certain motor vehicles to be equipped with seat safety belts, 1964 January 22 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 12)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to certification by dealers on sales of used motor vehicles, 1964 January 22 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 13)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to shopping centers, 1964 January 22 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 14)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to dimensions of certain vehicles, 1964 January 22 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 15)
  - Authorizing the City of Buffalo to grant and convey permanent easement in a sixty-six foot wide piece of land in LaSalle Park..., 1964 January 22 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 16)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to certain peace officers designated as police officers, 1964 January 23 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 17)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to income executions and repealing section fifty-two hundred thirty-one of such law related thereto, 1964 January 23 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 18)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to issuance of driver's licenses and learners permits, 1964 January 23 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 19)
  - To amend chapter nine hundred eighty of the laws of nineteen hundred and sixty two, entitled "An act in relation to the merger of the University of Buffalo into State University of New York...", 1964 February 06 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 20)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to the service of a summons upon filing notice of pendency, 1964 February 10 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 21)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to motor vehicles equipped with flashing lights, 1964 February 11 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 22)
  - To amend the insurance law, in relation to joint underwriting of group health insurance for persons aged sixty-five and over, 1964 February 12 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 23)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to speed limits established within areas, 1964 February 17 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 24)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to proper garnishee ..., 1964 February 18 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 25)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to fees of county clerks, 1964 February 18 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 26)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to making certain mechanical corrections therein, 1964 February 18 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 27)
  - To amend the insurance law, in relation to group accident, group health and group accident and health insurance, 1964 February 18 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 28)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to the powers of certain peace officers, 1964 February 18 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 29)
  - To amend the penal law, in relation to the possession of firearms and weapons which simulate a machine-gun..., 1964 March 02 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 30)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to jurisdiction of courts and special sessions, 1964 March 02 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 31)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to inspection of tires, 1964 March 12 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 32)
  - To amend the education law, in relation to the position of assistant to a district superintendent or superintendents, 1964 March 02 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 33)
  - Making an appropriation to the department of education for the purpose of making an additional apportionment of moneys to...the towns of Cheektowaga and Lancaster..., 1964 March 23 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 34)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to minimum specifications for retreaded tires, 1965 January 06 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 35)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to requiring certain motor vehicles to be equipped with seat safety belts, 1965 January 06 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 36)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to required equipment of school buses, 1965 February 10 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 37)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to arrest by a police officer without actual possession of a warrant, 1965 March 02 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 38)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to payment of costs for preparation of the return in appeals from courts of special sessions..., 1965 March 17 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 39)
  - To amend the education law, in relation to exemption from liability of nurses rendering first aid or emergency treatment, 1965 March 17 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 40)
  - To amend the retirement and social security law, in relation to establishing a policemen's and fireman's retirement system...[1 of 2], 1966 January 05 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 41)
  - To amend the retirement and social security law, in relation to establishing a policemen's and fireman's retirement system...[2 of 2], 1966 January 05 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 42)
  - To amend the local finance law, in relation to issuance of bonds by school districts..., 1966 January 05 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 43)
  - To authorize the commissioner of motor vehicles to receive...certain moneys for the purpose of having the State of New York design, construct and test a prototype safety car..., 1966 January 12 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 44)
  - To amend town law, in relation to exclusions from central fire alarm systems in the Town of Cheektowaga, Erie County, 1966 January 19 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 45)
  - To amend the civil practice law and rules, in relation to service of legal papers upon a county, 1966 January 19 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 46)
  - To amend the county law, in relation to composition, duties and powers of the legislative body of a country, 1966 January 19 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 47)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to certain peace officers designated as police officers and the use of force resisting arrest, 1966 February 01 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 48)
  - To amend the public health law, in relation to stopping of motor vehicles by police officers to search for illegal narcotics, 1966 February 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 49)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to shopping centers, 1966 February 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 50)
  - To incorporate the Millgrove Volunteer Exempt Fireman's Benevolent Association, and providing for it's powers and duties, 1966 February 08 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 51)
  - To amend the vehicle and traffic law, in relation to following fire apparatus, 1966 February 14 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 52)
  - To amend the code of criminal procedure, in relation to arrest by an officer without a warrant, 1966 February (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 53)
  - To amend chapter five hundred sixty of the laws of nineteen hundred sixty-two, entitled "An act to incorporate the Sloan Exempt Volunteer Fireman's Benevolent Association...", 1966 March 31 (Box 1 (1-Legislation), Folder 54)
- Special Committees, 1959-1966; 2; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The series contains drafts of special committee reports with related correspondence, notes, reports, clippings, and printed matter. Material includes work on the New York State Law Revision Commission, Traffic Safety Committee, Temporary Commission to Revise the Penal Law, and Insurance Committee.
  - Administrative Law [1 of 2], 1964 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 55)
  - Administrative Law [2 of 2], 1964 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 56)
  - Committee on Codes, 1960-1962 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 57)
  - Ethics and Guidance Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 58)
  - Insurance Committee, 1961 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 59)
  - Joint Legislative Committee on Motor Vehicles and Traffic Safety, 1963 October 11 (Box 1 Continued (2-Special Committees), Folder 60)
  - Law Revision Commission [1 of 2], 1963 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 1)
  - Law Revision Commission [2 of 2], 1963 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 2)
  - Law Revision Commission, 1963-1964 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 3)
  - Law Revision Commission: Comments on the Draft Administrative Procedure Act, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 4)
  - Law Revision Commission, Second Projects Report, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 5)
  - Law Revision Committee, 1959-1963 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 6)
  - Law Revision Committee, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 7)
  - Law Revision Committee: Administrative Procedure Act, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 8)
  - Law Revision Committee: Business Brokers' Oral Contracts for Finder's Commissions, 1963 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 9)
  - Temporary Commission on Revision of the Penal Law and Criminal Code [1 of 3], 1964 March (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 10)
  - Temporary Commission on Revision of the Penal Law and Criminal Code [2 of 3], 1964 March (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 11)
  - Temporary Commission on Revision of the Penal Law and Criminal Code [3 of 3], 1964 March (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 12)
  - Traffic Safety Commission, 1960-1962 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 13)
  - Traffic Safety Commission, 1963 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 14)
  - Traffic Safety Commission, 1964; 1966 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 15)
  - Traffic Safety Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 2 (2-Special Committees), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1958; 1960-1961; 1963-1966; 3; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series includes letters, newspaper clippings, reports, memos, vouchers and printed materials.
  - Assembly Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2 Continued (3-Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - Assembly Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2 Continued (3-Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Assembly Correspondence [1 of 2], 1961 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Assembly Correspondence [2 of 2], 1961 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Assembly Correspondence [1 of 2], 1963 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Assembly Correspondence [2 of 2], 1963 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Assembly Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Assembly Correspondence, 1965 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Assembly Correspondence, 1966 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence), Folder 7)
- Subject Files, 1961-1965; Undated; 4; 1.0 cubic ft.
  The subject files relate to research in various fields of interest and include papers on Mr. Volker's professional development as a lawyer. There is material on alcohol and drug addiction with reference to the legal statutes of New York State.
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control Law, New York State Moreland Commission, 1963 (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Assembly District, Erie County, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Assembly, General, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - The Association of the Bar of the City of New York, Committee on State Legislation, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Civil Practice Act, 1962-1963; Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Conflicts of Interest in Automobile Liability Insurance Cases [1 of 2], Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Conflicts of Interest in Automobile Liability Insurance Cases [2 of 2], Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Dictation of Defamatory Matter by Lawyer to his Secretary as Publication of a Libel, 1964; Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - First Projects Report, 1964 (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - The Judicial Conference of the State of New York, 1965 February (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Liability for Damages from Explosions..., Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Limitation of Term of Infants Contracts for Certain Professional Employments, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Lost or Destroyed Instruments Essential to the Existence of a Right, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Narcotics, 1961-1962; Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Nature of Interest in Property Condemned by a Railroad..., Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Pure Waters, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Real Property Actions and Proceedings Law, Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Requirement of Hospitalization..., Undated (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Report by the New York State Commission of Investigation Concerning Pistol Licensing Laws..., 1964 November (Box 3 Continued (4-Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Summary of Legislation [1 of 2], 1965; Undated (Box 4 (4-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Summary of Legislation [2 of 2], 1965; Undated (Box 4 (4-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Temporary Commission of Investigation Sixth Annual Report, 1964 March (Box 4 (4-Subject Files), Folder 3)